<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<metadata>
    <journal-meta>
        <journal-id>Orbit: Writing Around Pynchon</journal-id>
        <issn>2044-4095</issn>
        <publisher><publisher-name>Orbit: Writing Around Pynchon</publisher-name></publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
        <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7766/orbit.v2.1.47</article-id>
        <title-group>
            <article-title>To Cry from Within or Without? Pynchon and the Modern – Postmodern Divide</article-title>
        </title-group>
        
        <contrib-group>
            
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
                <name><surname>Harvey</surname>
                    <given-names>Lawrence Russell</given-names>
                </name>     
                <xref ref-type="aff">
                    
                </xref>
            </contrib>
        </contrib-group>
        
        <aff>Barton Peveril College, UK</aff>
        
        <pub-date pub-type="pub">
            <year>2013</year>
        </pub-date>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, Lawrence Russell Harvey</copyright-statement>
            <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
                <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
            </license>
        </permissions>
        
        <self-uri>https://www.pynchon.net/owap/article/view/47</self-uri>
        
        <abstract><p>This article interrogates the demarcation of modern and postmodern literature within the context of a critical and inter-textual reading of Thomas Pynchon’s <italic>The Crying of Lot 49</italic>. Approaching Pynchon’s text from what is essentially a formalist perspective, this reading readdresses the question as to whether or not <italic>The Crying of Lot 49 </italic>breaks through to a mode of fiction beyond modernism itself. Critics such as Brain McHale have forwarded <italic>The Crying of Lot 49</italic> as a paradigmatic late modernist work; a work that does not break through to a mode of fiction beyond underlying epistemological presuppositions. Via a comparative reading that draws on the work of Paul Auster, Bret Easton Ellis <italic>et al.</italic>, it is argued herein that McHale’s otherwise scholarly reading is somewhat myopic. In short, it is argued that although Pynchon’s heroine is driven by an epistemological agenda, the text-scape she inhabits is postmodern.</p></abstract>
    </article-meta>
</metadata>
